Okay בוקר טוב. boker tov. Today's דף daf is כ״ב, Kaf-Bet, but
we are a bit behind so we're going to try to go
really quickly today, relatively quickly. We pick up at the very bottom
of כ״א עמוד א׳ Kaf-Alef Amud Alef and the question we're dealing
with is: what is the story about צידי רשות הרבים, tziddei reshus
harabim, the edges of רשות הרבים, reshus harabim, if an animal eats
from it, is that considered רשות הרבים reshus harabim or not? And
as I said, it doesn't really seem to be a question of
where the animal is standing versus where the animal is eating. It
seems to be like if it was a clear רשות היחיד, reshus
hayachid, then the food's in רשות היחיד reshus hayachid that tastes in
רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid, you know, it's a רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid,
that's a רשות הניזק. reshus hanizak. The point is that the צידי
רשות הרבים tziddei reshus harabim is this grey zone which is quite
close, which is quite associated with רשות הרבים. reshus harabim. Is that
רשות הרבים reshus harabim or not? So anyway, it was a debate
of רב Rav and שמואל. Shmuel. Everybody agreed if the animal walked
into רשות הרבים reshus harabim and was doing real incursion, it would
be seen as a not רשות הרבים. reshus harabim. But if the
animal just turned its head and ate from it, that's stuff that
it has access to while it's in רשות הרבים, reshus harabim, that
might be considered רשות הרבים. reshus harabim. That was the first phase.
The second phase, and let's pick up for the second interpretation, we'll
pick up from this at the bottom of כ״א עמוד א׳. Kaf-Alef
Amud Alef. It says the following: והכי אתמר. vehachi itmar. Okay דאיכא
דאמרי de'ika d'amri במחזרת bemachzeres כולה עלמא לא פליגי דחייבת. kula alma
lo pligi dechayaves.
If the animal just turns its head and eats from the side,
everybody agrees that it is חייבת, chayaves, which is interesting, which means
that that's considered to be a רשות הניזק reshus hanizak even though
the animal has access to it. Since it has to turn its
head, it's not directly in front of the animal, so since it
doesn't have direct access to it when it's in רשות הרבים, reshus
harabim, that's considered רשות הניזק. reshus hanizak. So that's a very narrow,
if you want, a very broad definition of רשות הניזק reshus hanizak
or a very narrow definition of רשות הרבים. reshus harabim. So that's
important. כי פליגי במקצה ממקום רשותו לרשות הרבים. ki pligi bemuktzeh mimakom
reshuso lereshus harabim.
Somebody basically has allowed the רבים rabbim to use his property. He
has his property, it's adjoining the רשות הרבים. reshus harabim. He makes
a fence here and he allows the first foot or two for
the רבים rabbim to use. He doesn't give up title, he allows
them to use it. So it's not צידי רשות הרבים tziddei reshus
harabim because this actually now becomes a space that the main usage
of the רבים, rabbim, it's part of the main street, people actually
go there regularly. It's not off the side. I mean maybe it's
physically off the side, but in terms of usage, it literally is
used as part of רשות הרבים. reshus harabim. But technically he still
has title. So is that considered רשות הניזק reshus hanizak or is
that considered רשות הרבים? reshus harabim? That לשון lashon
מקצה, muktzeh, like yeah set aside, yeah exactly. והכי אתמר. vehachi itmar.
אמר רב amar Rav לא שנו אלא במחזרת. lo shanu ela bemachzeres.
When is it that it's considered רשות הניזק reshus hanizak is if
the animal turns its head and it's actually not functionally part of
רשות הרבים. reshus harabim. אבל במקצה ממקום רשותו לרשות הרבים, aval bemuktzeh
mimakom reshuso lereshus harabim, if
he actually gives his place to be used by the רבים rabbim
and it's functionally part of רשות הרבים, reshus harabim, פטורה, ptura, it's
exempt. Interesting, because now the גמרא Gemara has רב Rav being more
exempting and שמואל Shmuel more obligating. ושמואל אמר u'Shmuel amar אפילו במקצה
ממקום רשותו לרשות הרבים afilu bemuktzeh mimakom reshuso lereshus harabim חייבת. chayaves.
No, even in that case it's חייבת chayaves because technically it is
not the רשות הרבים. reshus harabim. ונימא בבור ברשותו קמיפלגי. veneima bebor
bireshuso kemifligi. Maybe this debate can be mapped onto the debate of
what's the story if it's a בור, bor, if I dig a
well on my property and then I מפקיר mafkir my property and
my property adjoined רשות הרבים. reshus harabim. So I let everybody use
the space around it, so effectively I made all the property around
my well רשות הרבים. reshus harabim. Okay, מפקיר
ברשותו,
mafkir
bireshuso,
I'm not מפקיר mafkir the בור. bor. The בור bor is still
my domain. Now that's not the classic בור, bor, which is I
dig it in רשות הרבים. reshus harabim. So I've got in that
case there's two things. Number one is I don't own it
and my digging of it was in a space I didn't have
a right to dig it and I basically completely violated the space
of the רבים rabbim by digging my well here, whereas when I
did it it was totally okay. And now even though I've מפקיר-ed
mafkir it and let everybody use the space around it, I could
still say yes, but you have no right to use my בור.
bor. This is still my בור. bor. I still retained title. You
have no right to use it. So that becomes an interesting debate
whether or not I'm חייב chayav in that case. Now what does
that have to do with this issue? So the גמרא Gemara is
going to say what it has to do with this issue is
that now basically I've put my fruit here, okay, in this space
that I've given over for the רבים rabbim to use. Now the
fruit, let's say an animal were to trip on it, right? Okay,
this becomes the בור. bor. Would I be חייב chayav or not?
So if you'd say that's similar to the case, I had a
right to put my fruit there, it is my property, but then
I allowed everybody to use that space, but I still own that
fruit. So it's sort of like the בור bor that I own
and I've allowed people to use the space around it. So the
assumption is going to be the following: if I would be חייב
chayav if your animal got damaged on that type of a בבור,
bebor,
then once I've got that, then that בור bor somehow is seen
as in violation and then you have a right to seize the
fruit. You have a right to, you know, because the whole בור
bor is in a type of in like violation and that's a
גמרא Gemara later that if I sort of put a hazard in
רשות הרבים, reshus harabim, not a בור, bor, people have a right
to seize it as their own.
Seize it and take it? Yeah, for themselves.
And there's a later discussion, but yeah, it's a type of a
קנס. knas. Correct, let's, I, this is complicated because it draws on
another סוגיא, sugya, so I want to move through this quickly so
we can get to the next one. Let's take a look. Okay.
רב
דאמר פטור, Rav d'amar patur, Rav that says you're exempt when the
animal eats that fruit, קסבר בור ברשותו חייב, kasavar bor birshuto chayav,
that this is a type of a בור bor in your domain
and you'd be חייב, chayav, and therefore since you've done this בור
bor in violation, somebody, the animals are not going to be liable,
somebody's not going to be liable for damage. ושמואל אמר חייב, uShmuel
amar chayav, and Shmuel says you're חייב chayav for the animal eating
the fruit, קסבר בור
ברשותו פטור, kasavar bor birshuto patur, that you'd be פטור patur on
this, and therefore you're not in violation, and therefore the animal is
eating fruit in your רשות reshus where the fruit is not in
violation and therefore going to be חייב. chayav. אמר לך רב, amar
lach Rav, Rav would tell you, no, לעולם אימא לך, le'olam eima
lach, I tell you, בעלמא, be'alma, בור ברשותו פטור, bor birshuto patur,
normally
a בור bor in your own domain you're פטור, patur, even if
you were מפקיר mafkir the space around it, okay? So if that's
true, if you're פטור, patur, so here too, so here you should
say חייב chayav because there was nothing wrong by putting the fruit
there, so why isn't the animal who eats from it obligated? So
the גמרא Gemara says no, ושאני הכא דאמר לאו כל כמינך דמקרבת
לה לפירותיך לרשות הרבים ומחייבת לה לתוראי, v'shani hacha d'amar lav kol
kaminach d'makrevas lah l'peirosecha l'reshus harabbim u'mechayavas lah l'sorai,
because the owner of the animal could say, you had no right
to put your fruit right near the רשות הרבים reshus harabbim and
now you're going to make me obligated. So it's true, we can't
use this בור bor idea as a basis of exemption. Forget בור.
bor. Like you weren't even thinking about it before we mentioned it
two minutes ago. Okay. Why are you פטור? patur? They're פטור patur
because functionally, like we assumed all along, functionally, although technically this is
still your רשות, reshus, functionally you've made it part of רשות הרבים.
reshus harabbim. You've made this רשות reshus part of רשות הרבים reshus
harabbim functionally. I have a right to use that as I have
my animals go through it, right? It's not שדה אחר sadeh acher
which has a different functional use. Okay. So once I have that
right to do it, you're responsible. If you put your fruit right
there, you're asking for trouble, right? Just like we would have said
before we mentioned the whole idea of בור. bor. If it's functionally
רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, I'm פטור. patur. You can't blame me if
you're the one that put your fruit there. What? I don't know,
when you when you were מפקיר המקום, mafkir hamakom, maybe. Okay. ושמואל
אמר, uShmuel amar, now Shmuel would say, בעלמא בור ברשותו חייב. be'alma
bor birshuto chayav. Normally you're חייב. chayav. Now this is a little
more complicated. If normally you're חייב, chayav, by putting this here you
did something wrong, so why should I be obligated if my animal
damages it? דבשלמא de'bishlama בור, bor,
no, it could even say you're
חייב. chayav. דבשלמא de'bishlama בור bor איכא למימר לאו אדעתיה. ika lemeimar
lav adateih.
No, because here's the difference, because by a בור bor I can
say I'm חייב chayav because you don't see a well, right? A
well is like flush with the ground and it's not obvious. The
whole problem with a well is that you, it's like
you trip in it. It's like it's not raised from the ground.
It's easy to miss it. אלא פירות מי איכא למימר לאו אדעתיה
הא חזי להו, ela peiros mi ika lemeimar lav adateih ha chazi
lehu, you can see it. All right, which means if this was
a well, you would be חייב, chayav, but because it's fruit, okay,
the animal can see the fruit. So because you can't be, so
therefore you cannot be מחייב mechayav me for making a בור. bor.
And since you can't be מחייב mechayav me for making a בור,
bor, this fruit doesn't constitute a בור bor because it's obvious and
visible. Therefore you did not have a right to take it or
damage it. And since you didn't have a right to take it
or damage it, so now you'll be חייב chayav because technically this
is your רשות. reshus. So basically what the גמרא Gemara says is,
this was just a distraction, a distractant, a complicating factor which we're
just going to bracket. Okay? Either it's, meaning yes, you could be,
I don't care, you could be פטור patur on your בור, bor,
but that's not the reason, meaning
whatever
you hold by the בור, bor, okay? Either this isn't a בור
bor that you'd be חייב chayav on, so that doesn't give you
a right to damage it, okay, and even if a normal בור
bor you'd be פטור patur on, we can just have this discussion
of whether this is considered רשות הרבים reshus harabbim and ignore the
בור bor question, which is what we were doing anyway in the
first place. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara tries to link it to
this question of is it a בור bor that gives you right
to seize the property and says look, let's not, forget the בור
bor issue. That's not relevant. Let's just deal with this on its
own.
What do you
decide about אדעתיה adateih is?
Okay, that's going to be discussions when we get to בור. bor.
Okay, let's keep on moving. Okay. לימא מחזרת תנאי היא, leima mechazereth
tanna'ei hi, let's see if מחזרת mechazereth is a debate of תנאים.
Tannaim. דתניא בברייתא, detanya be'braisa, אכלה מתוך הרחבה משלמת מה שנהנית, achla
mitoch harachavah meshalemes mah shehenis, מצדי הרחבה משלמת מה שהזיקה, mitzidai harachavah
meshalemes mah shehezika, דברי רבי מאיר. divrei Rabbi Meir.
That's what our משנה mishna says, the words of רבי מאיר. Rabbi
Meir. From the street it's מה שנהנית, mah shehenis, that's רשות הרבים,
reshus harabbim, the side of the street is רשות הניזק, reshus hanizak,
דברי רבי מאיר ורבי יהודה. divrei Rabbi Meir v'Rabbi Yehuda. רבי יוסי
ורבי אלעזר אומרים אין דרכה לאכול אלא להלך. Rabbi Yossi v'Rabbi Elazar
omrim ein darkah le'echol ela lehalech. An
animal doesn't eat, it just keeps on moving. So what does that
mean? רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi and the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, we
assume that means that he's saying it doesn't eat from the side
of the street, so it should have kept on moving, the side
of the street is a רשות הניזק. reshus hanizak. So that's what
the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says, that the side of the street
was a רשות הניזק. reshus hanizak.
So the גמרא Gemara says
אלא מחזרת איכא בינייהו. ela mechazereth ika beiniyahu. Okay. It stood on
the side of the street, that's what it's חייב chayav, *chayav*. But
if it just turned its head, it would be פטור patur *patur*.
Okay, רבי יוסי Rebbe Yose *Rebbe Yosei* סבר *savar* no, משלמת מה
שהזיקה *meshalemet mah shehizika* even if it just turns its head. An
animal should be moving straight; it shouldn't be turning its head. So
even if it just turned its head, that's considered a space the
animal shouldn't be going, and that's essentially רשות הניזק reshus hanizak *reshut
hanizak*. But it says no, not necessarily. דכולי עלמא *dekulei alma* מחזרת
mechazeres. *mechazeret* עיקר היזיקא שמור *ikar heizeka shamor*. We could say that
everybody, that מחזרת *mechazeret* is either always going to be
חייב chayav, *chayav* because it's not we assume that it's not in
the
normal access range of the animal, animals shouldn't be turning their heads
and it's not part of רשות הרבים reshus harabim *reshut harabim*. Or
you would say it's פטור patur, *patur*, it is in the access
range, animals do sometimes turn their head and it's connected to רשות
הרבים reshus harabim *reshut harabim* and it's associated with it and it's
going to be פטור patur *patur*. You could say one way or
the other. והכא *vehacha* so what's this discussion about? ובער בשדה אחר
*uv-ve-ar bi-sdeh acher* קמיפלגי *kamiflegi*. Now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going
to go suggest something totally radical. Okay, maybe it's a fundamental definition
debate of what ובער בשדה אחר *uv-ve-ar bi-sdeh acher* means. מר סבר
mar savar? *mar savar* ובער בשדה אחר *uv-ve-ar bi-sdeh acher* ולא ברשות
הרבים *velo b'reshut harabim*, okay, which is meaning any as long as
it's not רשות הרבים reshus harabim. *reshut harabim* and therefore צידי רחבה
*tzidei rechava* is not רשות הרבים reshus harabim *reshut harabim*. Fine. What's
the other opinion? ומר סבר *umar savar* ובער בשדה אחר *uv-ve-ar bi-sdeh
acher* ולא ברשות המזיק hamazik *velo b'reshut hamazik*. No, only the only
thing ובער בשדה אחר *uv-ve-ar bi-sdeh acher* is saying is that if
you bring your fruit into my domain, I can't be liable for
what my animal does. But any space that is not my the
המזיק *hamazik* domain, I'm going to be חייב chayav. *chayav*. So let's
remember a long time ago we said, right, you have
a continuum, right? You have רשות הרבים reshus harabim *reshut harabim* here,
okay, and you have רשות הניזק reshus hanizak. *reshut hanizak* here, okay,
right? And here, right, you have all this space in between. So
like here you have צידי רחבה *tzidei rechava*, okay, you know, you
have all you have remember we had רשות reshut של שניהם *reshut
shel shneihem* you might remember, right? We have a lot of types
of spaces, right, that are in between. Now, here I've got full
rights to go, here I've got no rights to go, and there's
a whole continuum of places in between. So until now that was
sort of our question of how do you define שדה אחר *sdeh
acher*? Does it have to be the real stuff that I completely
violate by going into? Or does it have to, you know, anything
else I'm going to be פטור patur, *patur*, right? That's one way
of sort of seeing the debate of צידי רשות הרבים tzidei reshus
harabim. *tzidei reshut harabim*. Or does it have to be only the
stuff that I have full right to be in and is the
standard use or whatever and anything that's a little off the beaten
path like צידי רחבה *tzidei rechava* that I'm going to then I'm
going to be חייב chayav *chayav*. That's one way of discussing the
debate of צידי רחבה *tzidei rechava* also. Whether you define שדה אחר
*sdeh acher* as רשות הניזק reshus hanizak *reshut hanizak*, or whether you
say what it means by שדה אחר *sdeh acher* is you're פטור
patur *patur* are you it's saying you're חייב chayav. *chayav* in רשות
reshut, הניזק *reshut hanizak*? So that's going to mean you're going to
be פטור patur *patur* in a wide range of things. Or do
you say you're פטור patur, *patur* in רשות הרבים reshus harabim *reshut
harabim* and you're going to be חייב chayav *chayav* in a wide
range of things? Everybody get that? Like that's like a classic way
of thinking about things that when you're defining something, the category that
you wind up defining, you say is the A, and everything else
is the not A. So the category you wind up defining winds
up being the narrower category, because most things in this universe live
in the not A space rather than in the A space. Okay?
So anyway, so are we basically saying you're חייב chayav *chayav* in
רשות reshut הניזק *reshut hanizak* or are we basically saying you're פטור
patur, *patur* in רשות הרבים reshus harabim *reshut harabim*? Anyway what the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* has now suggested is even more radical. What the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* has now suggested is when it says ובער בשדה
אחר *uv-ve-ar bi-sdeh acher*, what it really means is that the only
place you're פטור patur. *patur* is רשות המזיק reshus hamazik *reshut hamazik*.
Okay? But in every other place other than רשות המזיק *reshut hamazik*,
then you're going to be חייב chayav, *chayav*. You're going to be
even חייב chayav *chayav* in רשות הרבים reshus harabim *reshut harabim*, which
is like crazy. So let's take a look. Okay? ומר סבר *umar
savar* ובער בשדה אחר *uv-ve-ar bi-sdeh acher* ולא ברשות המזיק *velo b'reshut
hamazik*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says and so you're going to
be חייב chayav *chayav* even in רשות הרבים reshus harabim? *reshut harabim*.
Now where it's exactly getting that from in this debate, I don't
know.
One minute, let me just check רש"י Rashi *Rashi* because I don't
even understand how that works out. זימנין דנכנסה שורו לחצר בעל הבית
שלא ברשותו ואכל ופטור *zimnin d'nichnesa shoro l'chatzer ba'al habayit shelo b'reshuto
v'achal u'patur*. But everything else you're going to be חייב chayav. *chayav*.
So, oh right, so the reason that when רבי יוסי ברבי אלעזר
אומר אין דרכה לאכול אלא להלך ein darka l'echol ella l'halech, *Rebbe
Yosei bar Rebbe Elazar omer ein darchah leechol ela lehalech* means that
wait, oh that's sounding like they're going to be more being מחייב
*mechayev* you. I don't even get how to read this, I gotta
tell you. Like what does רשות המזיק *reshut hamazik* explain?
Because if all it meant was to be פטור patur. *patur* exempt
in רשות המזיק *reshut hamazik* and you'd be חייב chayav. *chayav* in
רשות הרבים reshus harabim *reshut harabim*, I don't see anybody here saying
you're חייב chayav *chayav* in רשות הרבים reshus harabim? *reshut harabim*. Anyway,
let's see what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says. מר סבר Mar savar,
*mar savar* ובער בשדה אחר *uv-ve-ar bi-sdeh acher* ולא ברשות הרבים *velo
b'reshut harabim* ומר סבר *umar savar* ובער בשדה אחר *uv-ve-ar bi-sdeh acher*
ולא ברשות המזיק *velo b'reshut hamazik*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
ברשות המזיק *b'reshut hamazik*, the רשות *reshut* of the המזיק *hamazik*, you
don't need a פסוק passuk *pasuk* to tell you that. למה תורך
ברשותי מאי בעית *lama torcha b'reshuti mai bayit*? Who said you could
bring your fruit into my domain? So you don't have to exclude
רשות המזיק *reshut hamazik*. אלא דאילפא ורבי אושעיא דרו בה *ela d'Ilfa
v'Rebbe Oshaya d'ru bah*, fine. Next. Maybe the debate is not in
this ברייתא braisa. is not about מחזרת. Maybe the debate is אילפא
Ilfa ורבי אושעיה. ve-Rebbe Oshaya. Remember אילפא Ilfa ורבי אושעיה ve-Rebbe Oshaya
were those where when an animal's in רשות הרבים reshus harabim? and
another animal eats off the back or jumps on the back of
another animal, okay? So maybe that's what they're debating. Maybe the תנא
קמא Tana Kama is saying if it was anywhere in רשות הרבים
reshus harabim you're going to be פטור patur and רבי יוסי and
רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer are saying an animal just walks in רשות
הרבים. reshus harabim If an animal actually jumps on the back of
another animal in רשות הרבים reshus harabim then you're going to be
חייב, chayav. okay? So
when he says אין דרכה לאכול אלא להלך, ein darka l'echol ella
l'halech.
so what that means is you're telling me that anything it eats
in רשות הרבים reshus harabim, you're פטור, patur? I'm going to tell
you that there's things it could eat in רשות הרבים reshus harabim.
that it's not פטור p'tur? that it should have been walking and
it shouldn't have been eating. It shouldn't be jumping on another animal's
back and eating off the other animal's back. So you can't prove
from that debate that they are debating the issue of צידי רשות
הרבים. tzidei reshus harabim, Okay, so the גמרא Gemara doesn't reconcile doesn't
resolve the question of צידי רשות הרבים, tzidei reshus harabim but as
I said and that הוה אמינא hava amina there that it's the
פסוק is only talking about a רשות המזיק is very strange. I
don't understand how it would have explained the ברייתא. braisa. But as
I said, the interesting question it's a very interesting for me conceptual
question. One way of framing the question is, do we understand fundamentally
what we're saying here is if it's רשות הניזק you're חייב, chayav,
everything else you're פטור, patur and then we're going to say something
like חצר של שניהם, chatzer shel shneihem, צידי רשות הרבים tzidei reshus
harabim. etc. you're going to be פטור patur because it's not fundamentally
רשות הניזק. Or are we going to say no, fundamentally רשות הרבים
reshus harabim you're פטור patur. because there you've got a right to
be going and everybody's on their, you know, if you're leaving your
fruit there, it's, you know, it's at your own risk, etc. it's
פשיעת הניזק. peshias hanizak.
And anything that's not this overriding reason to be פטור, patur you're
going to be חייב. chayav So that's one way of explaining where
these middle cases around those middle cases. Another way to just say
it is everybody agrees fundamentally the definition is רשות הרבים reshus harabim
you're פטור, patur but how functional versus how formalistic are we going
to be in defining the nature of רשות הרבים? A place that's
associated with רשות הרבים that it sometimes has access to but is
not fundamentally doing the same function, it's other different ways of framing
exactly what the debate is of צידי רשות הרבים. But anyway, I
find that these these marginal cases are always very interesting because they
raise questions of exactly what's the nature of your definition. Yes.
רש"י Rashi says that it's that צידי מתוך הרחבה tzidei mitoch harachava
you're חייב chayav and תוספות Tosafos asks your question but that we
said before that it would be פטור.
patur Which were you talking about? About where it says מר סבר?
מר סבר, רבי
אלעזר ורבי יצחק Rebbe Elazar v'Rebbe Yitzchak both say המזיק of רשותו
reshuso חייב.
chayav We said before that it's פטור.
patur Yeah, yeah, but I wasn't even just worried about how we
said it before, I was just worried about how they read the
ברייתא. braisa Where were they reading that words in the ברייתא braisa.
to say that you were חייב chayav. in רשות הרבים? The first
position said משלמת מה שנהנית meshalemes mah shenehis and the second position
said אין דרכה לאכול אלא להלך. ein darka l'echol ella l'halech So
where was that language of אין דרכה לאכול אלא להלך ein darka
l'echol ella l'halech. saying that you're going to be פטור patur in
רשות הרבים? That sounds like more of a basis language you're going
to be... I just don't see how they fit it in the
words of the ברייתא. braisa. תוספות Tosafos just worried about making it
fit with the הוה דגמרא. hava d'Gemara. I'm just I don't see
how it parses the ברייתא. braisa. Okay. Anyway, that is their discussion
of so to what degree it's a very local discussion, certainly not
as broad and interesting as the question about, you know, what do
you call it? about זה נהנה וזה לא חסר. zeh neheneh v'zeh
lo chaser. But within our ארבע אמות arba amos if you would
of, you know, of ארבע אבות נזיקין arba avos nezikin and, you
know, and the case of שן ורגל shen v'regel to think why
is
שן ורגל shen v'regel פטור? patur. Is it because we're fundamentally חייב
chayav everywhere and רשות הרבים is a special פטור? patur Is it
fundamentally פטור patur everywhere and רשות הניזק is a special חיוב? chiyuv?
How do you deal with things that are technically not רשות הרבים
but functionally they are like רשות הרבים and so on? That I
think is what those questions were.
Well, actually צידי מתוך הרחבה tzidei mitoch harachava you're
now חייב, chayav right?
No, no, no, that was I didn't see that was like a
complete whatever, not a serious הוה אמינא, hava amina, I don't even
understand how it was reading the ברייתא. Beraita? Okay.
But point רש"י Rashi that רש"י Rashi says מתוך הרחבה mitoch harachava
נמי nami חייב chayav, לרבי יוסי. l'Rebbe Yose.
Yeah, I just don't see how that works within the words of
אין דרכה לאכול Ein darka l'echol. אלא להלך. How do those words
mean you're חייב chayav. מתוך הרחבה? mitoch harachava?
No, like קרן, keren, like it's not it's not אורחיה orchaya then
you're
חייב.
chayav אין דרכה לאכול. Oh, I see what you're saying. If it
normally doesn't eat, it doesn't normally have a right to eat even
in even in רשות הרבים, even... Oh, all right, okay, I see
what you're saying. Okay, it normally doesn't have a right to eat
even in רשות הרבים. Oh, right, okay, that's it. Right, thank you,
thank you, I don't know why it wasn't registering. Right. So the
הוה אמינא hava amina or what he's saying would be even in
רשות הרבים it should be doing nothing other than just walking. Walk,
right. So anything it's doing in רשות... it does no, we have
no license for it to be eating in רשות הרבים, right? That's
you're right, that's what it would be saying. So even in רשות
הרבים it would be חייב. chayav The only place it would be
פטור patur is if you brought your fruit into this guy's domain.
But once this animal is out in some general public space, right,
you're חייב chayav for everything it does, right. I'm sorry, I don't
know why it wasn't registering. Okay. So that's how the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* did want to read it, that it would be חייב chayav
*chayav* everywhere except in רשות המזיק *Reshut Hamazik*, but anyway, the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* immediately rejects that, right, that has never been a viable
thinking. The only question, the real question is, everybody is clear that
you're פטור patur *patur* רשות הרבים *Reshut Harabim*, the question is how
to frame it between these two.
And the המביע *Hamaveh*, that is המביע *Hamaveh*, right, in other words,
זה המבע וזה המזיק *zeh hamaveh vezeh hamazik*.
Right. Well, but yeah, but we read that as שן *shen* and
רגל *regel*. Let's look at the next משנה Mishnah, *Mishna*. הכלב והגדי
שקפצו מראש הגג ושיברו את הכלים משלם נזק nezek שלם מפני שהן
מועדין *Hakelav vehagidi shekaftzu merosh hagag veshivru et hakelim meshalem nezek shalem
mipnei shehen muadin*. Okay, so the dog and the goat, they jump
from the head of a, from the top of a roof, from
the roof top, and they break vessels below. That is נזק nezek,
שלם *nezek shalem* because they're מועד *muad*, which is, it's a type
of a רגל *regel* essentially. So we're doubling back, we did רגל
*regel* and שן *shen*, now we're doubling back to רגל *regel*. Okay,
and it's not like an אונס ones *ones*, it's something you could
have expected, okay, it's not a שינוי shinuy *shinui*. הכלב שנטל ha-kelev
she-natal, חררה *Hakelav she-natal
charara*, now there's going to be the case that we're going to
be focusing on.
A dog took a biscuit, you heard of this one earlier, we
had it earlier, it went to a גדיש *gadish*, and it went
to a haystack, אכל החררה והדליק הגדיש *achal hacharara vehidlik hagadish*, it
ate the biscuit and it lit a fire to the haystack. על
החררה משלם נזק nezek, שלם ועל הגדיש משלם חצי hitza. נזק *Al
hacharara meshalem nezek shalem veal hagadish meshalem chatzi nezek*. On the חררה
*charara* it pays full, on the haystack half, presumably it's a type
of a צרורות tzroros, *tzrorot*, okay. It's a שן *shen* by the
חררה *charara*, and presumably it's a type of a צרורות tzroros *tzrorot*,
it's incidental, it's not directly the body of the animal itself on
the haystack, but we will see about it. Actually, גדיש *gadish* is
not a haystack, it's a wheat stack, right? It's a wheat bundle,
it's much more expensive than a haystack. Yeah, a sheaf, whatever.
I can't really imagine a scenario of a dog or a goat
jumping off a roof where it's not suicide. It's a very big
רגל *regel*.
Well, and actually, doesn't want to jump down, jumping off,
and the dog, it
looks like a cat, it does tend to be. Right. And that
makes me wonder about the dog with the hot biscuit. It's hot.
Yeah, but I understand that the biscuit is in its mouth, the
biscuit's attached to
the- the ember's attached to the ember, or you're saying the biscuit
is hot? Yeah, I don't know, it's not easy
for a dog to pick up something that's burning hot.
Okay, I don't know what to tell you, the whole point of
this משנה Mishnah *Mishna* is that it is דרכו *darko*, so, alright,
so anyway, but I hear the question. טעמא דקפצו *Taama d'kaftzu*, the
reason is that they jumped. הא נפלו פטור patur? *Ha naflu patur*.
If they fell off the roof and broke something, you'd be exempt.
אלמא קסבר תחילתו בפשיעה וסופו באונס פטור patur. *Alma kasavar techilato bifshiya
vesofo be-ones patur*. So this is a classic question. You began you
were negligent, in the end something else happened. How was he negligent
having his dog up on the roof? Yeah, you were negligent having
your dog up on the roof, that it was because remember it's
a רגל *regel*, it means it's falling into חצר הניזק *chatzar hanizak*.
So you had your dog up on a roof where it would
have been reasonable to expect it could have, those questions aside, jumped
off of the roof and broke stuff in the- in the person's
property below, right? It's חצר הניזק *chatzar hanizak* below. So that's negligent
of you, but if you didn't have a certain degree of negligence,
you'd be exempt. So there's a degree of negligence, but then something
happened that was not to be anticipated, it fell off the roof.
So you have a מעקה *maakeh* that's not tall enough to prevent
dogs though?
Well, or you don't have a מעקה *maakeh*, I don't know. Okay.
So the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says פטור pattur. *patur*. So but
it sounds like that would- that you'd be פטור pattur? *patur*. תניא
נמי הכי *Tanya nami hachi*. הכלב והגדי שקפצו מראש הגג ושיברו את
הכלים משלם נזק שלם *Hakelav vehagidi shekaftzu merosh hagag veshivru et hakelim
meshalem nezek shalem*. If they jumped and broke, that's a type of
a רגל *regel*, it happened in חצר הניזק *chatzar hanizak*. נפלו פטורים
pturim. *Naflu p'turim*. If they just fell you'd be exempt. הא ניחא
למאן דאמר תחילתו בפשיעה וסופו באונס פטור pattur. *Ha nicha leman d'amar
techilato bifshiya vesofo be-ones patur*. That's good if you generally say, we're
not getting into this debate, this is a whole major debate elsewhere,
we're just briefly referencing it. If you generally say that if you
begin with negligence but then as a result of the fact that
you sort of, you know, you did your first act, something unforeseen
happened, okay, nevertheless that you're exempt, then that works. אלא למאן דאמר
חייב chayav. *Ella leman d'amar chayav*, but the one who says you're
חייב chayav? *chayav* because if it wasn't for your initial negligence this
unforeseen thing wouldn't have happened, okay, so it's all tied into your
initial negligence, מאי איכא למימר *mai ika lemeimar*, what can you say?
You should be חייב chayav *chayav*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
כגון שקירב כלים לגבי כותל *kegon she-keriv kelim legabi kotel*. No, no,
the case would be would be that the vessels were right up
against the wall, דכי קפצי לא נפלי עלייהו *de-ki kaftzi lo nafli
aleihu*, that you were not negligent to begin with because- because you
were only negligent because it would be reasonable to expect the dog
might jump, but if it had jumped, דקפיצה לא נפלי עלייהו *de-kfitza
lo nafli aleihu*, it wouldn't fall on them. When it jumps, you
know, you make, you know, you have a horizontal movement as well,
and it wouldn't have fallen on the vessels. So you were אונס
ones *ones* in regarding the vessels to begin with, there was never
any פשיעה *peshiya* regarding those vessels. אפילו תחילתו בפשיעה ליתא *Afilu techilato
bifshiya leita*. You wouldn't- didn't even start with any negligence. פשט pshat
*pshat*. אמר רב זביד משמיה דרבא *Amar Rav Zevid mishmeih d'Rava*. פעמים
שאפילו נפלו נמי חייב chayav *Peamim she-afilu naflu nami chayav*. There are
times even if it falls you're חייב chayav. *chayav*, even if you
say תחילתו בפשיעה וסופו באונס פטור pattur *techilato bifshiya vesofo be-ones patur*.
There are times you'd be חייב chayav, *chayav* even if it fell,
which means there are times you're being פושע poshea *poshea* even if-
even about falling, that falling is something to anticipate. What would be
those cases? משכחת לה בכותל רעועה *Mashkachat lah bekotel reuah*. It's a
shaky wall, so you should have expected it might have fallen off
the wall. So the גמרא Gemara,
*Gemara* says מאי ניהו *mai nihu*? איבעי ליה לאסוקי אדעתיה *ibei lei
le-asukei adateih*? דאדעתיה דנפלה לחוץ *d'adateih denafila lachutz*? Whatever reason the גמרא
Gemara doesn't assume shaky wall means you would assume the animal would
fall. So גמרא Gemara says סוף סוף לא נפל ארחא ונפל אינהו.
sof sof lo nafal archa ve-nafal inhu.
Okay, you might have been negligent that a brick would fall off
the wall, but that's not what happened. The brick didn't fall, your
animal fell off. Okay, כל שכן kol sheken סוף סוף sof sof
אונס הוא. ones hu. So we're back to that issue. In the
end, it wasn't to be expected the animal would fall off. So
the גמרא Gemara just gives the obvious answer: לא, צריכה בכותל צר.
lo, tzericha be-kosel tzar. It's a narrow wall. Narrow wall and shaky?
I don't know. Anyway, the point is you were negligent about the
animal falling off as well. So here's stupid enough to take your
animal up to a rooftop where the animal could fall off, and
you're negligent about that, then you would obviously pay for the falling
off as well. Okay. תנו רבנן, tanu rabbanan, our Rabbis taught. הכלב
והגדי שדלגו ha-kelev ve-ha-gedi she-dilgu ממטה למעלה. mi-mata le-ma'ala. So you have
a dog or a goat that is jumping from below up: פטורים.
That's considered to be unusual. That's what? I never heard a dog
should jump, I mean, I guess a dog might, I don't know,
you get a dog to beg, right? But would your dog actually
jump?
He'll jump. He'll jump like from a lower place to a higher.
Yes. Do dogs do that? Will a dog jump from the floor
like to the table? Yes.
From the couch to the table. Yes. Wherever.
So I don't understand this. That just exacerbates Dave's question, because it's
assuming it's natural for it to jump down and unnatural for it
to jump up. No, they'll jump up. How about goats? Anybody know
about goats?
Oh, they jump anything. I mean, mountain goats like jumping up all
the time.
I don't know what to tell you. I don't know what to
tell you. Okay.
tell you. Okay. מלמעלה למטה חייבין. mi-lemala le-mata chayavin. From above below
you're חייב. chayav.
We're just going to work with the assumption, somebody will be able
to do some research coming what the גמרא Gemara was talking about.
Anyway, for whatever reason, it says jumping up is unusual, jumping down
is usual. So jumping up you're going to be פטור. Now, there's
a question between רש"י Rashi and תוספות, Tosafot, does it mean פטור
which is שינוי shinuy and therefore you're going to pay half? Or
does it mean פטור it is so bizarre, so unusual, you're like
an אונס ones, and you pay nothing? All right. Anyway, רש"י Rashi
says you pay half. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara says, okay, so אדם
ותרנגול, adam ve-tarnagol, however, a person or a chicken שדלגו she-dilgu בין
מלמעלה למטה בין מלמטה למעלה, bein mi-lemala le-mata bein mi-lemata le-ma'ala,
whichever direction, חייבין, chayavin, you're חייב, chayav, because a person's always liable
for damages and I guess chickens are supposedly natural for them to
jump both ways. Don't ask me. והתניא, ve-hatanya, we're just going to
get through this one. והתניא ve-hatanya at the top of כ"ב kaf-bet
עמוד ב', amud bet, don't we teach in a ברייתא? הכלב והגדי
שדלגו בין מלמעלה למטה בין מלמטה למעלה פטורין. ha-kelev ve-ha-gedi she-dilgu bein
mi-lemala le-mata bein mi-lemata le-ma'ala pturin.
That the dog and the and the goat, whether it's above or
below, either direction are פטורין. pturin. People who have been saying that
it is... well, whatever. Anyway, so it's פטור both ways. How do
you deal with the fact that you said that it's only פטור
if it goes up and חייב chayav if it goes down? So
the גמרא Gemara says תרגמה רב פפא דאפיך מיפך. tirgama Rav Papa
de-afich mi-pach. The reason it's פטור both directions, whether it's going up
or down, is that it's like twisting in midair. Okay. בזיקירא? be-zikira?
The dog... כלבא בזיקירא, kalba be-zikira, the dog does something like some
type of a flip. וגדייא בסריכא, ve-gadayya be-sericha, and the and the
goat does some type of I don't know, of a of a
climbing on the wall. Anyway,
it does weird things. Okay? The dog and... and because it's doing
weird things, so it's not really whether it's jumping up and down
that makes it פטור. The reason it's פטור is because it's doing
these weird flips and jumps. So the גמרא Gemara says אי הכי
אמאי פטורין? ei hachi amai pturin?
So why are they פטורין pturin meaning the גמרא Gemara says if
that's the way it is,
somehow that should make it a type of a שינוי shinuy, and
half payment, but it shouldn't be completely exempt. So the גמרא Gemara
says פטור מן הנזק שלם וחייב בחצי נזק. patur min ha-nezek shalem
ve-chayav be-chatzi nezek. All right. I cannot... so it's fine, it's a
שינוי, it pays halfway. As I cannot worry too much about this
גמרא. Gemara We're going to move on. I don't understand what you
basically everybody here has said is that the actual natural thing is
the opposite of it. The basic principle is if it does something
natural you pay full, if it does it unnatural then depending on
how degree of unnatural and unexpected you might be considered a total
אונס oness and pay nothing, or if there's a tiny amount or
if it's not completely אונס, oness, right, then it gets into the
קרן keren category and you would pay half. Exactly how that's worked
out about up and down and doing flips I don't know, but
we're moving on.
And that's going to be whether it's a קנס knas or whether
it's a היזק. hezek.
Well, yes, as the two ways of understanding the half, yes. And
whether which line of נזק you're on. All right. We are now
going to turn to a very central סוגיא sugya and let's focus
on this. Okay. הכלב שנטל, the dog that takes the wafer. Okay.
איתמר, itmar, it was taught. רב יוחנן אמר אשו משום חציו. Rav
Yochanan amar esho mishum chitzav.
The fire is for... fire, why is the תורה Torah saying you're
חייב chayav. when you light a fire and it goes out and
does damage? So this is the core conceptual question about the nature
of the obligation of fire. Okay. So רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan says
it is a type... it is considered like your arrow. It's basically
you did the actual lighting of the fire and then the wind
took it, it's basically all a continuation of your initial action, so
it's like shooting an arrow, it's like you did it.
וריש לקיש אמר ve-Resh Lakish amar אשו. esho. grain. It's like the
thing you owned, you made something, a fire, and that escaped, like
your animal escaping, so you're liable for something that is yours and
the damage that something you owned did, that was yours did, but
not because you actually are seen as the person who did the
damage. All right, so very interesting questions. Now, there's a question here
חציו כחו, chitzav kocho, right? חציו כחו. chitzav kocho. Now, there are
there's some very important questions to be asked here before we even
get any further, which is number one, what type of אש eish
are we talking about? The אש eish in the תורה Torah is
something where I might be negligent but I'm not intentional. Okay, let's
say for example, we've got Michael's sack of grain right there, and
I'm trying to burn it down, and I basically sense where the
wind is coming from, okay, and I know that
the wind is going to get stronger in the next two minutes
or so, and it's going to be a strong backwind, I light
it here, okay, it's a straight path to Michael's grain, and I
step aside and let the wind come and do it or whatever,
right? So is that we're going to say that's ממונו? mamono? Like
at what stage is my intention and the likelihood of that כוח
אחר koach acher maybe would people agree that that actually would be
completely like I did it directly? Or maybe not. Is the bottom
line is the wind took it, I didn't take it, אדם המזיק.
adam hamazik. So that's like one question. Classic אש eish is if
there's negligence and not intention. What about if there's intention? I think
that's one thing to be asked. Like arson basically? Yeah. The well,
arson is you directly light it, here you let the wind bring
it. Okay, the other question to be asking is whether the גמרא
Gemara means this in כל התורה כולה kol haTorah kullah or is
it a specific question of what category of the אבות נזיקין avos
nezikin to put it into. For example, if you say אשו משום
חציו, eisho mishum chitzav, okay,
if I light a fire and I'm negligent about it, and let's
bracket the intention question, and I'm negligent about it and it goes
and spreads and God forbid it kills somebody, do I go into
גלות, galus, right? Is that like I murdered the person or not,
right? Or and according to, right, would would we apply the same
principle
by the definitions of רציחה. retzichah. Okay, or here's a question that
the נימוקי יוסף Nimukei Yosef asks. He says, if we say אשו
משום חציו, eisho mishum chitzav, when I light my fire and then
five hours later it burns down your house, it's like I burned
down your house. He says, why do we light שבת Shabbat candles?
He says, I light a candle right before שבת, Shabbat, and then
it continues to burn on שבת, Shabbat, so it should be like
on שבת Shabbat I'm making a fire. Now, that's a funny question,
he has an answer to that, his answer is is that even
if we say משום חציו, mishum chitzav, it doesn't mean you did
the act then, it means it's all seen from the very moment
you lit it as if you did the act, okay, so it's
like you lit, so even though the fire continues to burn on
שבת, Shabbat, what you did was before שבת. Shabbat. So if I
light my fire here and it burns down your house, yes, I
burned down your house, but I burned it down from the moment
I lit the fire. The נפקא מינה nafka mina would be, let's
say somebody lights a fire, ten minutes later it burns down his
neighbor's house, but before it burned down his neighbor's house, this guy
dropped dead. Okay, so he says, can you now collect from the
heirs? Would the heirs say no, when the fire burned down the
house my father was dead, so he wasn't burning down the house.
So clearly presumably we attribute the action to the moment of the
lighting of the fire. Okay, that's a separate question, but what I'm
sort of bringing up is the fact that he thinks you can
raise a שבת Shabbat question based on this discussion in the גמרא,
Gemara right? Is this discussion in the גמרא Gemara a general question
of how we look at fire, or is it no, the תורה
Torah says you pay damages when your fire burns something down. We
know that there are two categories of of paying for damages, when
you break destroy something and when your property destroys something. Which of
those two categories is the גמרא Gemara תורה Torah putting it into?
Within the laws of נזק, not within some general כל התורה כולה
kol haTorah kullah principle. Within the laws of נזק, which of those
two categories does it belong to? That's a very different type of
much more local and focused type of a question. Let's see what
the גמרא Gemara says. Okay, so איתמר. itamar. רבי יוחנן אמר אשו
משום חציו. Rabbi Yochanan amar eisho mishum chitzav. וריש לקיש אמר אשו
משום
ממונו. veReish Lakish amar
eisho mishum mamono. וריש לקיש מאי טעמא לא אמר כרבי יוחנן? veReish
Lakish mai ta'ama la amar k'Rabbi Yochanan? Why did ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish not say like רבי יוחנן? Rabbi Yochanan? אמר לך, amar lach,
he would say to you, חציו מכחו קא אזלי, chitzav mikocho ka
azlei,
because in a normal arrow your energy propels the arrow, it's all
your strength through the arrow. האי לאו מכחו קא אזיל, hai lav
mikocho ka azil, here you did one act and then the wind
came and did it, so you were the origin, you were the
thing that began the process, but it wasn't in the end your
energy communicated through the fire, so it wasn't your act.
ורבי יוחנן מאי טעמא לא אמר כריש לקיש veRabbi Yochanan mai ta'ama
la amar k'Reish Lakish that it's משום ממונא? mishum mamona? אמר לך,
amar lach, ממונא אית ביה ממשא. mamona it bei mamasha. הא לית
ביה ממשא. ha leit bei mamasha. Because your property has some substance
to it. This is like fire is not something that you owned.
really like oh now you might that's an interesting question can I
own fire? If you come and you steal you know talk about
זה נהנה וזה לא חסר *zeh neheneh v'zeh lo chaser* i have
a fire burning and you go ahead and you stick a stick
into my fire and you get a fire right that's what his...
but can you say you stole my fire? So there's a question
can you technically own fire? But what he's saying is is that
even if you can like own it and you know you made
a fire you have rights to it it's not the same type
of a thing as like your property that goes and does damage
this is just pure energy okay so it's not within the category
of when the תורה *Torah* says you're חייב chayav *chayav* when your
property goes ahead and does damage. So let's take a look. Now
by the way there's an interesting תוספות Tosafot
*Tosafos*
here
let's take a quick look at these two תוספות *Tosafos* אש משום
חציו eish mishum chitzav, *Eish mishum chitzav* תוספות *Tosafos* says לא שיעביר
בעצמו האש אלא כל מקום שפשע ולא שמר גחלתו חציו נינהו *lo
she'ya'avir b'atzmo ha'eish ela kol makom she'pasha v'lo shamar gechalto chitzav ninhu*.
So actually תוספות *Tosafos* says because it's also interesting right let if
you you know even if you are just negligent in the in
the flame that makes it your cheitz like who actually lit the
initial fire let's say right my wife went ahead and she let
and she lit the the the grill and then i she went
and then she walked away and then I was supposed to watch
it and I was completely negligent about it and then it spread
and I won't say well her fire she lit it so it's
my fire I was the one negligent so this becomes even more
interesting in abstracting the idea of what does it mean it's my
act? My act I didn't light the fire I was just negligent
about the fire and that makes it my fire and my act
how does it become to be the one who's responsible for?
I don't know let's say I made you my שומר *shomer* you
know there's ways in which you know I can transfer responsibility without
you being the one who actually you know did the act of
lighting it. So then the now the next תוספות *Tosafos* אש esh
משום ממונו *Eish mishum mamono* says כל אומר חיוב chiyuv. ממונא יש
בה ולא שיש שלו דאפילו הדליק באש של אחר חייב chayav *kol
omer chiyuv mamona yesh bah v'lo she'yesh shelo d'afilu hidlik b'eish shel
acher chayav*. This is like the flip i don't know not the
flip it's the same anyway it doesn't matter who owns it right
like you could have lit the fire okay but if I go
ahead and I take a fire that you lit and I light
somebody else's you know stack of grain with it I can't say
well it's your dog that ate the stack of grain it's not
you know so there's a way in which what תוספות *Tosafos* was
pointing out is whether it's חציו *chitzav* or ממונא *mamona* it's like
the the way it gets associated with me is not necessarily that
I own it or that I lit it the way in which
it gets associated with me is that I was yes you have
to establish why am I responsible for it but if I become
responsible and negligent about it or certainly if I'm intentional then that
makes it you know my fire my ממון mamon *mamon* and so
on so those two תוספות *Tosafos* are basically getting at the same
point which is and it's a bigger חידוש *chiddush* I think if
we say משום חציו *mishum chitzav* because we're really saying even if
you didn't do the physical act of lighting it it's your arrow
because of your negligence but it could also be your ממונא *mamona*
because of your responsibility and your negligence. Okay so now the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says like this
okay so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this בשלמא *Bishlama* now
תנן
*tenan* let's see how this works in our משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* הכלב
שנטל חררה *hakelav she'natal chararah* so the dog took the biscuit. בשלמא
למאן דאמר אש משום חציו bishlama le-man de-amar eish mishum chitzav, חציו
דכלבא הוא *bishlama l'man de'amar eish mishum chitzav chitzav d'kalba hu* so
if it's because of חציו *chitzav* so why do you pay half
on the גדיש *gadish* stack of grain? So if it's חציו *chitzav*
so the same way it's my could be my my arrow it
could be my dog's arrow so if I light a fire and
it spreads it's like I did it if my dog creates a
fire and it spreads it's like my dog did it. Okay so
therefore my dog burnt down the גדיש *gadish* my dog did it
but it did it indirectly that would be צרורות tzroros, *tzroros* that
would be half damages. חציו דכלבא *chitza d'kalba* אלא למאן דאמר אש
esh משום ממונו *ella l'man de'amar eish mishum mamono* but if it's
not seen like I did what my fire did I'm חייב chayav.
*chayav* because my fire is like I owned an animal that went
and damaged האי אש לאו ממונו דבעל כלבא הוא hai esh lav
mamono d'baal kelava hu. *hai eish lav mamono d'ba'al kalba hu*? This
fire is not the it's not my fire my dog made a
fire if my dog made a fire it doesn't become my fire
it's my dog's fire so if my dog owned a pet okay
I wouldn't have I wouldn't have to pay for the damage that
my that an animal owned by an animal that wouldn't happen right
the תורה *Torah* is only מחייב *mechayev* me for what my animals
do damage and for what so when my fire my dog does
damage I'm חייב chayav. *chayav* if my dog's fire does damage it's
not my fire and I'm not חייב chayav *chayav* for things that
my dog owned again not my dog did my dog owned that's
the concept here. Wait what why is that not intuitive?
Wait because it's like a CEO who's the boss of who's the
boss of someone that ultimate boss is right
so if you say that all of this is about negligence then
you're right then what difference does it make I'm responsible I'm negligent
and so on. Okay but again the whole sort of this whole
first half of בבא קמא *Bava Kamma* is about the balance between
pure negligence and the obligation you have to be negligent or but
you weren't negligent with your property. This fire wasn't your property. And
you weren't negligent with the things that your dog did. You were,
so your dog, you're not obligated to be, you're not to be
responsible for property that's owned by your dog. That's the גמרא. Only
for your property are you responsible for. And this is another situation
where your dog could own property. So you would own some even
like if we're bringing it to humans,
like you own, I assume if you own a person as property,
right?
Something that they own is not really, does not really belong to
them,
it really belongs to you.
Well,
that might be, but that could be like if you own a
slave, then what a slave owns does belong to you. But like
that might be a good, right? You know, but if you could
imagine that, you know, you could give property to a slave that
they own independent of their master, right? And you owned a slave
and your slave owned a dog, you would not be חייב chayav
for your slave's dog. Is that possible? Yeah, well yes.
So that would be, so dogs don't normally own pets, but here
this fire turned out to be the dog's, as it were, you
know, it's sort of what we're saying. But let's compare, let's compare
the dog to a minor, who is not a בר דעת, bar
daat, and if my four-year-old has a tricycle,
yeah, for, tricycle's not a good example, but my four-year-old has a
dog. Okay, now there, as we all know when we've bought pets
for our kids, exactly, it's really your dog, it's not your kid's
dog. So if you go ahead and you bought that dog for
your kid, right? Then it's your dog and you are responsible. But
if you go ahead and light this fire for your dog to
play with, it is your fire and you're חייב. chayav? But you
did not light this fire for your dog to play with. Your
fire, your dog went and made that fire. That is, if your
kid goes and picks up a stray dog and hasn't brought it
home yet, and that dog goes ahead and does damage, you're not
responsible for it unless you were directly somehow involved in that process.
And that's what's happening here. There you go.
And this is why רש"י'ס Rashi's reading that it's ממונא דבעל צרורה.
mamona d'baal tzerora. Is it what, is it, why רש"י'ס Rashi's reading
is more intuitive here because the ממון mamon is the בעל צרורה.
baal tzerora.
Yes, and what רש"י Rashi does do, now you could just point
out that it's not your dog's אש esh. and leave it at
that. But what רש"י Rashi also does is he says, actually, this
אש esh is owned by somebody. It's owned by the guy who
made the fire. Now he might be an אונס oness because you
might have made a fire in a nice protected way and some
neighbor's dog came in and grabbed it or whatever. So you're exempt,
so I made the fire, I'm exempt because you broke my fire
free out of my protected space. So it's my and it's not
and it's not you or your dog's fire, it's my fire. So
רש"י Rashi does make this discussion easier by redirecting us and saying,
and saying so because the real ownership of that is by the
guy who lit it. But I think that it's important to bracket
that and to just say regardless, like let's say it was a
הפקר hefker thing. It wasn't, so the ownership makes it not your
ownership, right? There is still a reality that I did not make
this fire, I don't own it, my dog made it. It's like
his good example, my kid picked up a stray animal, I'm not
responsible for it, right? Okay, so I'm responsible for things my kid
does, I'm not responsible for things the stray animal that my kid
picked up, who he doesn't even own and I don't have an
assumed responsibility for it yet, I'm not responsible for it. Okay, so
that's the גמרא'ס Gemara's point that it is not ממונא דבעל כלבא.
mamona d'baal kelava. Okay, so אלא מאן דאמר אשו משום ממונו, ella
man d'amar ishu mishum mamono, האי אש esh. לאו ממונו דבעל כלבא
הוא. So it's not the ממון mamon of the owner of the
dog and it's not, and since it's not directly his property and
again as הלל Hillel pointed out, as רש"י points out it's the
property of the guy who owns it, but even besides that it's
not directly the property of the owner of the dog, so he
should be exempt. So אמר לך ריש לקיש, amar lach Reish Lakish,
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish will stay with you. הכא במאי עסקינן דאדי
אדויי. hacha b'mai askinan d'adi aduye. You're right. The reason you pay
half is not because the fire spread. If the fire spread then
and you didn't know about it, again you weren't directly negligent about
it, then you're פטור on what the fire does. So the reason
you pay half is the dog threw even צרורו. tzeroro. It's well
the צרורה tzerora because you have to explain why you pay half
is that the dog threw the coal or he threw the as
he, what do you call it? The biscuit with the coal and
that burnt the immediate space of contact. So where the coal burnt
the immediate space of contact that's direct, that's like it threw a
fire and that's like something ripped with its sharpness, you know, or
broke with its weight, so this broke with its heat. So the
immediate space of contact is not yet the concept of אש. eish.
As people understand that אש eish. is I make a fire and
it spreads, right? If I actually take a torch and I burn
something, everybody says that's my action, that's not אש. eish Okay, that's
not ממון or חצי. If I throw a torch and the immediate
place it first burns, everybody will say that's כוחו. kocho. Okay, it's
when it spreads afterwards that we can have a debate but the
immediate point of contact that's my action or that's my כוח. koach.
So the dog threw the biscuit or threw the ember, the immediate
point of contact is כוחו. kocho. It doesn't, though the
That's directly where it came in contact and where it burned, that's
where you pay half. The rest of the spreading, you're totally פטור
*Patur*. Okay? Now, פשט pshat *Pshat* of the משנה Mishnah *Mishna*. The
משנה mishnah *Mishna* sounds like you're חייב *Chayav* half for everything that
it burns. All right? So ריש לקיש Reish Lakish, *Reish Lakish* says,
"So the גדיש *Gadish* is like the immediate thing, meaning the immediate
point of impact on the גדיש *Gadish*?" "Yes, immediate point of impact.
The same way if it was a rock, the immediate thing the
rock broke you pay half for, if it's an ember, the immediate
thing the ember burned, you pay half for. But any further spreading,
that's ממון *Mammon*, that's the ממון *Mammon* of the כלב *Kelev*, and
essentially therefore you pay nothing."
"But he says it's פטור *Patur*
for the גדיש *Gadish* though." "Because right, because that's where it spreads."
"It spreads." "Right." So the גמרא *Gemara* says, "למה מדדייה אדייה אדחררה
משלם נזק שלם אדמקום גחלת משלם חצי נזק *Lama medaddyei addyei ad
hachararah meshalem nezek shalem ad mekom gechelet meshalem chatzi nezek*.
That's where the כלב *Kelev* hit, that's not yet spreading of a
fire, that's the direct act, or the indirect, it's כחו *Kocho*, but
that's clearly כחו *Kocho*, it's like throwing a rock, and that you
pay half. ועל הגדיש כולה פטור *ve'al hagadish kullah patur*.
But on the entire sheaf, then it's spreading, and then you're פטור
*Patur* because we told אש eish? משום ממונו *Eish mishum mammono*, and
this is not your ממון *Mammon*, this is something your dog did."
"Yes, really, the difference between the rock that breaks something and a
projectile that has potential for damages beyond it, like a bomb. You
know, like this torch." "Right." "It's a כחו *Kocho* but it's built
into it, the damages that it's going to cause."
"Yes, but that's what we said, but because we're conceptualizing that extended
damage as ממון *Mammon* and not as חטא *Cheit*, then you're פטור
*Patur* on that. Right? I mean you're right, but that's the חידוש
*Chiddush*. רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* would say you're חייב *Chayav*."
"How does this whole thing work with תוספות *Tosfos*? Doesn't תוספות *Tosfos*
say that even if it's someone else's ממון *Mammon* if you light
it you're חייב *Chayav*?"
"Yes, so if you were directly negligent, if you saw your dog
doing this, presumably according to תוספות *Tosfos*, right, the question is what
are the circumstances that trigger your responsibility and your negligence? Right? But
that goes back to our analogy of once your kid brings the
pet home, then you might become responsible." "Only if you knew about
it." "Only if you knew about it. Right? So it could be,
right, that if you actually saw your dog and you were in
a place to intervene and you didn't or whatever, then at some
point maybe it becomes your אש eish *Eish*. But that's not necessarily
the case. So I mean you know it could have been interesting
why the dog did it, but if it's become your אש eish.
*Eish* then you'd be חייב *Chayav* full, you wouldn't be חייב *Chayav*
half, right?" "All right. So the גמרא *Gemara* says like this.
Okay. For רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*, רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* would say
דאנח אנוחי *deanach anochei*. No, no, no, it could be that it
just set the coal down. על החררה ועל מקום גחלת משלם נזק
שלם *al hachararah ve'al mekom gechelet meshalem nezek shalem* on the on
the biscuit and the place where it was put down it's full
because it didn't throw it, it directly put it down, so that's
like גופו *Gufo* actually, not כחו *Kocho*. ועל הגדיש משלם חצי נזק
*ve'al hagadish meshalem chatzi nezek*. The spreading, that's a spreading is a
case of כחו *Kocho* or צרורות tzroros *Tzeroros* because אש eish, משום
חציו *Eish mishum chitzav* and that would be half."
"What if the dog did throw it?" "If what?
If the dog threw it and then the first place it hit
was כחו *Kocho* and then it spread, so that becomes the question
of how do you פוסק *Pasken* about כח כחו *Koach kocho*? Okay,
so תוספות *Tosfos* and the ראש *Rosh* debate the whole question about
how do we wind up פוסק *Paskening* about כח כחו *Koach kocho*.
Would you pay a quarter, would you pay nothing, would you pay
full, like three possible..."
"But why the difference between putting it down and throwing it? Like
seriously, in other words it's still going from your body to another
place outside of you, only far away or close."
"No, because even if we say that צרורות *Tzeroros* are half, okay,
if an animal... I mean look, we haven't really directly... first of
all the question is what it means put it down. If you...
I mean if you directly go ahead... like I'm gonna cause a
spill. Anyway, if you take ahead...
to go ahead
and take a torch and do this, that's considered even though it
went through the torch..." "Your hand." "You put a torch against something
and you burn and right, at that place where it hit, that
would be גופו *Gufo*, that wouldn't be כחו *Kocho*. You're still attached
to it." "It's an extension of you." "Yeah, exactly. Okay.
According to רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* is there any situation where one
would be חייב *Chayav* on an entire... an entire fire?
I mean even the stuff that happens afterwards that goes well beyond..."
"So the גמרא *Gemara* is going to deal tomorrow with the concept
of כלו לו חציו *Kalu lei chitzav*. What is considered your חטא
*Cheit* might be the extent you could have anticipated had you not
been negligent from the outset, right, whereas what happens maybe beyond a
certain point, that's no longer your חטא *Cheit*. Okay, so the גמרא
*Gemara* will discuss that."
"Like the California wildfire, acres and acres."
"Right, I understand. Let's see if we can manage to turn the
page. Okay, so the גמרא *Gemara* says like this: תא שמע *Ta
shma*, come and hear. גמל טעון פשתן ועובר ברשות
הרבים *gamal ta'un pishtan ve'over bireshus harabim*. So you have a camel
carrying flax and it's passing through a רשות הרבים *Reshus harabim*. נכנס
פשתנו לתוך חנות *nichnas pishtano letoch chanut*. So the flax goes into
the store, ודלקה בנרו של חנוני Chanvani *vedalka benero shel chanvani*, and
it got lit by the candle of the storekeeper in the store,
but you were overburdened, your camel and it was, you know, that's
why the flax was going into the store. Okay. והדליק את הבירה
*vehidlik es habirah*, and then it lit a fire that inflamed the
whole building. Okay. Well, no, the בירה *Birah* here was like the
whole building. Okay, פשיטא *Pshita*. Right. בעל הגמל ba'al ha-gamal חייב *ba'al
hagamal chayav*. The owner of the camel is חייב *Chayav*. הניח חנוני
Chanvani נרו מבחוץ *hiniach chanvani nero mibachutz*. The shopkeeper left his candle
outside... but it was with the חנווני chanvani who put his candle
where it shouldn't be, put it outside the store and he knows
that animals are walking by, so חנווני חייב, chanvani chayav, the חנווני
chanvani is חייב because it's the חנווני's chanvani אש. So when the
חנווני chanvani put it outside and he knew camels were walking whatever,
so that was sort of like the camels were like a רוח
מצויה, ruach metzuyah, so it was the חנווני's chanvani אש. Okay, what
our פשט is going to be is why is the בעל הגמל
ba'al ha-gamal חייב and what's the nature of that חיוב. chiyuv רבי
יהודה אומר בנר חנוכה פטור. Rabbi Yehuda omer be-ner Chanukah patur. And
this is like the only time that חנוכה Chanukah gets mentioned in
the משנה, mishnah that if it was a חנוכה Chanukah light then
the חנווני chanvani is פטור because he has a right to light
his חנוכה Chanukah lights outdoors. Okay, we're going to have that משנה
later on. But
anyway, here's our question is not the second phrase of when the
חנווני chanvani is חייב, that's an אש that is you're being negligent
with. It's the first case in which the בעל הגמל is חייב.
So בשלמא למאן דאמר אש משום חציו, if it's אש משום חציו,
חציו דגמל הוא. chitzav de-gamal hu. So it's like your camel's acts
that went and created the fire. Now the funny thing what that
is is that then you'd have to say that when it says
חייב it means חייב חצי, chayav chatzi, right? Because it was the
case of צרורות, which is also not פשט of the משנה because
the second part of the משנה it says the חנווני chanvani is
חייב when his candle's on the outside means he's חייב full. But
the first half it says you're חייב if the flax goes in,
right? Presumably that makes it what? Like a type of a צרורות
or some- a type of a צרורות, right? So then you would
be paying half. Now of course what people here might be thinking
is: one minute, based on what we've been discussing until now, if
you see the flax that's caught fire and then you're negligent then
maybe it becomes your fire, right? But that's assuming you could have
interfered and stopped it. The presumption here is is that this all
happened, your negligence was not that you didn't stop it once it
lit fire, your negligence was that you loaded up the, you know,
too much of the of the flax on your, on your camel.
Okay? So it's never your fire really, right? Because of- people listen
here, right? By the time it catches fire, it's too far gone.
So it's basically your negligence was you were negligent with your sort
of animal whatever, so at most it's a type of a צרורות
you'd be paying half. But at least we could explain why you'd
be חייב. I mean if you wanted to be you could be
really radical and say, and here's an interesting idea, right? You've got
a fire, I've got a, I know you have a fire over
there, I've got a big container here of lighter fluid that has
a crack in it
and I know that if I just leave it here, it's going
to crack open and spill to your fire and make it into
this big thing and I go ahead and I'm negligent and I
leave it there. Okay? Am I considered to be פושע with an
אש? Should it have to start as my fire or the fact
that I know it's going towards a fire can make it sort
of, you know, like my fire? So that would be a way
of thinking about this case of the flax of the donkey that
actually no, I have flax, I know people have fires in their
house, I know I have an overburdened donkey with flax, so that
becomes my fire now. But that's not where the גמרא is going.
The גמרא assumes you didn't light the fire whatever, the most that
can happen is is that it can become once it catches fire
it's going to become the act of the donkey and then you
would be paying presumably half. Yes?
You don't even have to go so far as to say that
fire becomes yours in some way. You just say that it's actually
the flax that did the damage, not the fire. But that's not
true.
I mean in the, you know...
No, the flax acted as fuel but then the fire did the
damage. I mean what you're trying to say is I think the
same thing, I mean just another way, right?
It's an overburdened flax pile that causes this fire to become something
that is damaging.
Right, but then that ultimately is that then you become- anyway, but
that would be a way to go to make it like you
take ownership because of what you could have anticipated. But that does
not seem to be the way the גמרא is dealing with it.
So let's take a look. Okay? So the גמרא says בשלמא למאן
דאמר משום חציו חציו דגמל הוא. bishlama le-man de-amar mishum chitzav chitzav
de-gamal hu. And then presumably you'd pay half. אלא למאן דאמר משום
ממונו האי אש לאו ממונו דבעל גמל הוא. ela le-man de-amar mishum
mamono hai eish lav mamono de-ba'al gamal hu. It's not, you know,
it's not your fire, it's the חנווני's fire. He's אונס, he's not
liable. You shouldn't- and you're not liable because again once it became
a fire you weren't negligent, you were אונס once it became a
fire, right? So therefore why are you חייב? And you're not חייב
for fires that your camel lights, your camel goes and lights the
fire and it spreads, you're not חייב for it. So אמר לך
ריש לקיש הכא במאי עסקינן דמסכסכת כל הבירה כולה. amar lach Reish
Lakish hacha be-mai askinan di-mesachseches kol ha-birah kullah.
The animal is directly, it's not just the fire spreading with the
wind, the animal is directly walking around with the flax burning- burning
flax on its back and directly burning the entire- the entire building.
So how does that help? Your- so the גמרא says אי הכי
אימא סיפא. ei hachi eima seifa. Well, so I guess it helps
it because then well, it would help it because then it would
be I guess the direct act of the camel. Okay, so you
got it? The flax is burning on the camel's back and it's
directly going and it's not the fire spreading, directly burning, walking around
the building and burning it. So it is basically the direct act
of the camel.
It's so- it's sort of- it's sort of like the גמרא about
מקום הגחלת. makom ha-gecheles. It's making it all into מקום הגחלת. makom
ha-gecheles. So the גמרא says
אי הכי אימא סיפא. ei hachi eima seifa.
If the חנוני Chanvani puts the candle on the outside, the חנוני
Chanvani is חייב. If it is מסכסכת, mistachsachet, if the animal is
directly sort of, you know, hitting against the building or whatever, אמאי
חייב? amai chayav? Why is it, the way תוספות did it, why
is the חנוני Chanvani the only one who's חייב, right? Then it's
not like an אש that spread, then the חנוני is, the camel,
I
meant to say donkey and it's camel here, whatever, doesn't matter. Yeah,
it's a camel, I keep saying donkey, anyway. That then the camel
is directly doing it, so maybe it's also this guy's אש. If
my camel came and picked up a torch of yours and directly
with the torch in its mouth burned things, okay, so if you
were negligent, you should be paying for אש, but it's also my
animal is directly using your fire and directly doing an act and
I should also be חייב. So if it spread, we can say
whose fault was it? Your fault, my fault, it's either your fire
or my fire. But if it's not spreading, if it's directly being
used and that's why I'm חייב, I, the owner of the camel,
then that should be even if you were negligent with the fire,
I should actually have some חיוב still, some obligation. So the גמרא
says: בשעמדה. beshe'amdah. Okay, well the animal stopped. So how does that
help us? How does that explain why I'm not חייב here? בשעמדה
וסיכסכה כל שכן דחנוני פטור, beshe'amdah vesichsechah kol sheken deChanvani patur, the
גמרא says, if it stopped, then certainly even if you put the
fire on the outside, I should be able, my camel is directly
torching this building, okay, I should be able to intervene and stop
it and why, you know, why are you liable for everything? Or
at least, you know, I certainly have liability here even if you
put the candle on the outside. So the גמרא says: ובעל גמל
חייב, uba'al gamal chayav, and I should be חייב. So אמר רב
הונא בר מנוח משמיה דרב איקא הכא במאי עסקינן כגון שעמדה להטיל
מים. Amar Rav Huna bar Manoach mishmei deRav Ika hacha bemai askinan
kegon she'amdah lehatil mayim. Okay, that the animal had to stop and
is now urinating. And because it's urinating, it can't be moved. Okay,
you can't get the animal to move once it's standing there and
urinating. So now let's just sort of spell this out, spell it,
like, just read the next two lines.
רישא בעל גמל חייב דלא איבעי ליה לאפושי בטעינה. Reisha ba'al gamal
chayav delo ibai lei le'afushei bete'inah. So here's the scenario: okay, again,
according to ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish? it cannot be that the fire
spread. Because if the fire spread, it's ממונו דגמל mamono degamal and
I'm not חייב for ממונו דגמל. mamono degamal. Okay, it should only
be that the fire was directly in contact. People understand why that's
true for ריש לקיש? Reish Lakish If my animal does something with
a fire, for ריש לקיש Reish Lakish, the only way I'm going
to be חייב is if it directly, you know, uses the fire,
not if the fire spread. So the camel came with the flax,
lit the fire, and now directly, you know, stood where it was
and urinated, and as it was standing, without the fire spreading, it
was directly coming into contact with the building and burning it down.
So in that case, well, okay, it was a direct act of
the animal. I was negligent because I overloaded the camel. רישא בעל
גמל חייב דלא איבעי ליה לאפושי בטעינה. Reisha ba'al gamal chayav delo
ibai lei le'afushei bete'inah. I shouldn't have overloaded it with flax, and
anything that happened afterwards is as a result of my negligence. It
was regular, it was directly the body of the animal, and you
know, it was not, the fire didn't spread, it was directly used
and I'm חייב. How about the case in the end where the
חנוני puts the fire on the
outside? סיפא חנוני חייב דלא איבעי ליה לאנוחי נרו מבראי. Seifa Chanvani
chayav delo ibai lei le'anuchei nero mibara'i. You shouldn't have put the
fire on the outside. Fine, but let's still explain why I'm not
חייב. Because what happened is you put the fire on the outside,
it started with your negligence. I didn't overload my camel. I wasn't
negligent. I shouldn't have expected that your candle would be on the
outside. You were negligent. Fine, you started negligent. But then my animal
takes the fire and is using it. Why am I not negligent
right now by not intervening? So there the answer is I can't
intervene, it's standing and it's urinating, it's beyond my control right now.
Okay, so the same way you say it was obvious that I
couldn't intervene when the fire was spreading, we've created a scenario where
I can't intervene even when the animal is directly using the fire.
So bottom line is, it was a little complicated, but bottom line
is it all boils down to: for ריש לקיש, you can never
have me חייב for if my animal lights the fire and the
fire spreads. The only thing you can have me חייב for is
if my animal directly using the fire on the place that it
is, you know, that is directly burning with that fire. So this
case of the camel, we have to say the case of directly
using the fire, and the reason that I'm פטור when the fire
is on the outside, my animal is directly using it even though
you were negligent with your fire on the outside, why am I
פטור? Is the case that it's urinating and there's no way right
now that I can intervene. So I'm an אנוס onus right now,
and since you were negligent and I wasn't and I continue to
not be negligent because now my animal is urinating, so then I
continue to remain פטור. Okay? The camels are still the stars, David,
the camels are the stars. The camels are still supposed to be
שותפים.
shutfim. Camels are still
supposed to be שותפים. shutfim. They are all שותפים shutfim in that
path. And therefore, if the first one stopped for a good reason,
he's פטור. Now the גמרא asks, what about the case where the
משנה said they were all running and they're all פטור? The גמרא
says this refers to ערב שבת. Erev Shabbat. Because on ערב שבת,
Erev Shabbat, everyone has a רשות to run for the needs of
שבת. Shabbat. And since you have a רשות, even if you run
and you hit someone who is walking, you're פטור. This is what
איסי בן יהודה Issi ben Yehuda says, רץ פטור, ratz pattur, someone
who is running is פטור because it's a מצוה. mitzvah. But the
גמרא asks, we have a משנה that says if one is running
and one is walking, the runner is חייב? And the גמרא answers,
that's specifically on a weekday. On a weekday you don't have a
רשות to run, but on ערב שבת Erev Shabbat you do.